{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This slaveowner lived at the Oak Hill and Ash Lawn-Highland plantation estates.</em> As a governor, this man had the slave rebel Gabriel Prosser hanged. This lieutenant at the battle of Trenton holds the flag in Emanuel Leutze's painting <em>Washington Crossing the Delaware</em>. With Robert Livingston, this Virginian helped negotiate the Louisiana Purchase. For 10 points, name this politician who later presided over the Era of Good Feelings as the United States' fifth president.", "answer": "James <b><u>Monroe</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em>A photograph of the early days of this structure shows Conrad Schumann jumping in the</em> <em>direction of the viewer</em>. After the death of Peter Fechter near this structure, a wreath was placed by a mayor in his memory. The \"Death Strip\" ran in the middle of this structure, offering no cover. Despite Walter Ulbricht's claims it would not be built, construction on it began in August 1961. For 10 points, name this structure built by East Germany to dissuade emigration.", "answer": "<b><u>Berlin Wall</u></b> [or <em><b><u>Berliner Mauer</u></b></em>]  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>Filippo Pacini was the first person to isolate the causative agent of this disease.</em> During a pandemic of this disease in 1832, riots broke out in Liverpool over dead bodies. If this disease was found aboard a ship, the \"Yellow Jack\" flag would be raised to signal a quarantine. In the first show of epidemiology, the source of an outbreak of this disease in London was traced to a specific pump by John Snow. For 10 points, name this disease that causes watery diarrhea.", "answer": "<b><u>cholera</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JL"}, {"question": "<em>A leader of this country implemented a cap-rank system concurrently with his Seventeen-article constitution.</em> Beate Sirota helped draft a provision for a document in this country which mandates legal equality between men and women. Article 9 of this country's constitution provides for a Self-Defense Force, but outlaws war. For 10 points, name this country whose constitution was created by Douglas Macarthur's staff following its defeat in World War II.", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em>This player's exaggerated autobiography was co-written with reporter Al Stump</em>. This man's mother murdered his father just three weeks before he was called up to the majors. He lost a batting title because an opposing team helped the more well-liked Nap Lajoie win one. This man had a hitting record broken in 1985 by Pete Rose. For 10 points, name this fiery Detroit Tigers player known as the \"Georgia Peach,\" who had over 4,000 career hits.", "answer": "Tyrus \u201cTy\u201d <b><u>Cobb</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This man was sidelined for two weeks in a campaign after he hurt his knee on a car door</em>. This man foolishly promised to visit every state in an election he lost. He declined an investigation into voting fraud perpetrated by Richard Daley in Illinois, effectively conceding a close national race. For 10 points, name this sitting vice president and Republican who lost the 1960 presidential election to John F. Kennedy.", "answer": "Richard Milhous <b><u>Nixon</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>The use of this system was once denoted with the Latin abbreviation</em> st.n<em>.</em> This system was developed by Aloysius Lilius and introduced in the papal bull <em>Inter Gravissimas</em>. Its 1752 adoption in Great Britain was not actually met by mobs demanding, \"Give us back our eleven days!\" For 10 points, name this still-used system of determining the date, which superseded the Julian calendar.", "answer": "<b><u>Gregorian</u></b> calendar  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em>This man's book, The Truth, was plagiarized from John Humphrey Noyes</em>. This man told the jury that convicted him that they were \"low, consummate jackasses.\" This person's speech against Winfield Scott Hancock was not taken seriously by Republicans in the 1880 election. He reportedly shouted \"I am a Stalwart of the Stalwarts\" when killing a man at a Washington D.C. railroad station. For 10 points, name this assassin who killed President James Garfield.", "answer": "Charles Julius <b><u>Guiteau</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MC"}, {"question": "<em>This composer included \u201cThe Golden Willow Tree\u201d in his \u201cOld American Songs.\u201d</em> He expanded a piece, originally one of eighteen commissioned by Eugene Goossens in 1942, into the finale of his <em>Third Symphony</em>. A ballet by this composer, which depicted a colony of Shakers in central Pennsylvania, was choreographed by Martha Graham and featured the hymn \u201cSimple Gifts.\u201d For 10 points, what composer wrote a <em>Fanfare For The Common Man</em> and <em>Appalachian</em> <em>Spring</em>?", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Copland</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<em>During this crisis, Locofocos plundered Eli Hart\u2019s store in the \u201cFlour riot.\u201d</em> A 25% decline in cotton prices helped cause this event. The Deposit and Distribution Act, passed during this crisis, required the distribution of budget surpluses to states, creating pet banks, whose failure deepened this crisis. Due to this event, a later President signed the Independent Treasury Act. For 10 points, name this economic crisis which brought down the Presidency of Martin Van Buren.", "answer": "<b><u>Panic</u></b> of <b><u>1837</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A man with this epithet lost his duchies of Saxony and Bavaria in the 1180s for opposing the</em> <em>Hohenstaufens.</em> A Henry of the Welf dynasty with this nickname was a rival of Frederick Barbarossa. Opposite the unicorn, one of them is a supporter of the coat of arms of the United Kingdom. A winged one, which symbolizes Saint Mark, in turn symbolizes Venice. For 10 points, name this animal whose \"heart\" was a nickname for Richard I of England.", "answer": "<b><u>lion</u></b>s [or <b><u>Henry the Lion</u></b>; or <b><u>lion</u></b> rampant; or winged <b><u>lion</u></b> of Venice; or Richard I <b><u>Lion</u></b>heart]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Plutarch's first pair of</em> Lives <em>parallel this mythical figure with Romulus for their roles in</em> <em>founding cities.</em> This victor over the Pallantidae volunteered for a contest held in honor of the dead boy Androgeus. In another story, this son and successor of Aegeus fled the island of Naxos while his lover was still sleeping there; this man had previously received a golden thread from that lover, Ariadne. For 10 points, name this mythical king of Athens who slew the Minotaur.", "answer": "<b><u>Theseus</u> </b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A man won this specific position after his opponent accused him of being a \"bad Jew\" for</em> <em>marrying a Gentile</em>. The funeral for a man who held this post took place at Williams Arena and held an overly partisan tone that angered conservatives. A man who held this specific post died in a 2002 plane crash and was named Paul Wellstone. A current holder of this post is a former <em>Saturday Night Live</em> comedy writer. For 10 points, name this political position held by Al Franken.", "answer": "<b><u>Senator</u></b> from <b><u>Minnesota</u></b> [or senior <b><u>Senator</u></b> from <b><u>Minnesota</u></b>; or junior <b><u>Senator</u> </b>from <b><u>Minnesota</u></b> prompt on just \u201cSenator\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>When this ruler abdicated the throne, he left behind a series of precepts that began \u201clife is like</em> <em>walking along a long road shouldering a heavy load.\u201d</em> This man was advised by the navigator William Adams. This man was protected from warriors of the Iga clan by his loyal vassal Hattori Hanzo. This last of the three great unifiers led the victorious Eastern forces at the Battle of Sekigahara. For 10 points, name this first leader of Japan\u2019s final Shogunate.", "answer": "<b><u>Tokugawa</u></b> Ieyasu", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>One party was not able to march to this battle until the full moon due to the Carneia</em>. After the losing cavalry left, the victorious commander in this battle attacked when a 5-5 tie among the Strategoi was broken by the Polemarch (<b>pr. PO-le-mark</b>), Callimachus. 4 ranks of hoplites in the center and 8 on the flanks were used by Miltiades to defeat the forces of Datis here. For 10 points, name this victory for Athens over Persia, after which a messenger ran 26.2 miles back to Athens.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Marathon</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man's repeal of a car tax on his 1st day in office eventually added 4 billion dollars to his</em> <em>state's deficit.</em> Veterans of Pete Wilson's administration returned as staff for this man, who accused opponents of being \"economic girly-men.\" Phil Angelides lost a 2006 election to this man after this man signed the first greenhouse gas restrictions of any US state. For 10 points, name this husband of Maria Shriver, an Austrian-born former governor of California and actor.", "answer": "Arnold <b><u>Schwarzenegger</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This man condemned the Boston Tea Party as a \"savage mobility\" that had no place in</u></b></em> <em><b><u>politics.</u></b></em><b><u> A cartoon opposing this man emphasized the towns of Salisbury, Haverhill, and</u></b> <b><u>Methuen along the north side of Essex County in the northeast of this man's home state.</u><u>In</u></b> <b><u>1798, this man (+)</u>went with Virginian John Marshall and South Carolinian Charles Cotesworth Pinckney on a failed diplomatic mission to (*)</b> France. This Massachusetts man succeeded George Clinton in his highest office in 1810. For 10 points, name this second Vice President of James Madison, whose attempt at redistricting Massachusetts was likened to a salamander.", "answer": "Elbridge Thomas <b><u>Gerry</u></b>", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The Scottish urban planner Patrick Geddes created a 1925 \"plan\" for this city's layout.</u></b></em> <b><u>This city shares its name with a translation of the political novel</u> </b><em><b><u>Altneuland.</u> </b></em><b><u>One area of</u></b> <b><u>this city postdates but now contains the residential area (+)</u>Neve Tzedek. This city is home to the Habima theater and a city center aroundRothschild Avenue. The growth of this city, whose name literally means (*)</b> \"spring hill,\" caused the much older nearby city of Jaffa to dwindle until this city absorbed it. For 10 points, name this 2nd-most populous city of Israel.", "answer": "<b><u>Tel Aviv</u></b>-Yafo, Israel [do not accept or prompt on \"Jaffa\" or \"Yafo\"]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>As a young child, this king was ceremonially anointed by Pope Leo IV on a visit to Rome.</u></b></em> <b><u>While fleeing from a defeat, this man legendarily let a peasant woman\u2019s cakes burn. This</u></b> <b><u>man was the subject of a biography by the bishop Asser, who helped him translate (+)</u></b> <b>Latin works. This man defeated the Great Heathen Army at the Battle of Edington and forced the (*)</b> Danish king Guthrum to convert to Christianity. This man built a series of <em>burhs</em> and reformed the military to defend against further Viking attacks. For 10 points, name this Anglo-Saxon king of Wessex nicknamed \u201cthe Great\u201d.", "answer": "<b><u>Alfred</u></b> the Great [or <b><u>Alfred</u></b> I]  {I}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Eve Sussman \"animated\" one of this man's paintings in the live action film</u> </b></em><b><u>89 Seconds at</u></b> <b><u>Alc\u00e1zar. A historical painting by this man shows troops of Ambrogio Spinola standing by</u></b> <b><u>about thirty upright spears on the right side as (+)</u>Justin of Nassau hands over the key to a Dutch city besieged in 1526. This artist trained the Moorish painter Juan de Pareja. This painter of (*) </b><em>The Surrender of Breda</em> showed his patron Philip IV in a mirror in the back of a painting showing a dog and some dwarfs around the Infanta Margarita. For 10 points, name this Spanish painter of <em>Las Meninas.</em>", "answer": "Diego <b><u>Velazquez</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>In April 2015, Barack Obama announced a multi-week training program for 75,000 new</u></b></em> <em><b><u>workers with these objects, including many veterans.</u></b></em><b><u> The discoverer of the p-n junction,</u></b> <b><u>Russell Ohl, also improved greatly on early selenium-based designs for these things.</u></b> <b><u>Ronald Reagan had these objects (+)</u> removedfrom the White House, undoing an installation ordered by his predecessor had during the (*)</b> 1979 oil crisis. For 10 points, name these products manufactured by Solyndra, which collapsed after received maligned loans from the US Department of Energy.", "answer": "<b><u>solar panel</u></b>s [or <b><u>solar cell</u></b>s; or <b><u>photovoltaic cell</u></b>s; accept <b><u>solar</u></b> power industry until \"objects\"]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A species of zebra is named after a holder of this position, who resigned after his son-in-law</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Daniel Wilson was accused of trafficking an award.</u> </b></em><b><u>This office greatly diminished in</u></b> <b><u>prestige after \u201cla seize mai,\u201d when one of its holders dismissed his rival (+)</u>Jules Simon. Raymond Poincare held this post throughout World War I, Felix Faure held it during the (*)</b> Dreyfus Affair, and Adolphe Thiers took control of it at the start of the Third Republic after the Paris Commune. For 10 points, name this chief executive position of a European country.", "answer": "<b><u>President of France</u></b> [or <b><u>French President</u></b>; or <b><u>President</u></b> de la Republique <b><u>francaise</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This ruler insulted envoys sent by the Yongle Emperor and later died on campaign against</u></b></em> <em><b><u>him.</u></b></em><b><u> This man defeated the Tughluq Dynasty after he set his camels\u2019 tails on fire to scare</u></b> <b><u>off the other side\u2019s elephants. The historian Ibn Khaldun failed to convince this man not to</u></b> <b><u>sack (+)</u>Damascus. This ruler captured Bayezid the Thunderbolt at Ankara and his defeat of Tokhtamysh split up the (*)</b> Golden Horde. He was succeeded by his son Shah Rukh and was buried at the Gur-i-Amir mausoleum in his capital of Samarkand. For 10 points, name this Turko-Mongol conqueror nicknamed for his lame leg.", "answer": "<b><u>Timur</u></b> [or <b><u>Tamerlane</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "TR"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Alexander Malcolmson financially backed and formed a partnership with this man.</u> </b></em><b><u>This</u></b> <b><u>man's namesake \"-landia\" was a failed colony designed to extract rubber in Brazil. This</u></b> <b><u>man published four volumes on what he called \"The World's Foremost Problem\" under</u></b> <b><u>the title (+)</u></b><em><b>The International Jew, </b></em><b>which began as articles in his newspaper the </b><em><b>Dearborn </b></em><b>(*) </b><em>Independent.</em> He legendarily quipped that his first successful product could be had \"any color, so long as it is black.\" For 10 points, name this industrialist who enhanced the assembly line so as to mass-produce the Model T.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Ford</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The \"Age of\" a monarch of this empire partly titles Fernand Braudel's study of the</u></b></em> <em><b><u>\"Mediterranean World,\" which actually spans millennia.</u> </b></em><b><u>This country was defeated</u> </b><em><b><u>by</u> </b></em><b><u>the</u></b> <b><u>Vicomte de Turenne at the 1658 Battle of the Dunes. This empire used professional soldiers</u></b> <b><u>in (+)</u> square formations called</b><em><b>tercios</b></em><b> in the 17th century as it struggled to hold the</b> (*) Low Countries. For 10 points, name this empire which France forced to sign the Peace of the Pyrenees in 1659, nineteen years after the Iberian Union broke apart with the secession of Portugal from it.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Spain</u></b> [or Reino de <b><u>Espa\u00f1a</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}], "bonuses": []}